Guide to the Stephen Crane Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Stephen Crane Papers,
[ca. 1895]-1908
Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900.
9 linear ft (1,269 items in 21 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078666
Biographical Note
Scope and Content
Letters addressed to the Cranes from various members of the Crane and Howorth families, and from prominent literary figures such as Joseph Conrad, Henry James, H.G. Wells, George Bernard Shaw, Hamlin Garland, Elbert Hubbard, and Rider Haggard. A number of these letters relate to Mrs. Crane's activities after Crane's death, but the majority have to do with life at Brede Place in Sussex. Also present are a number of holograph manuscripts of Stephen Crane's literary works and manuscripts and typescripts of other material which he dictated. There is a group of stories and articles by Cora Crane, some pictures, photographs, art, and memorabilia. Also, seventy-four books from Crane's library, many of them signed.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Cataloged Material
Series II: Arranged Series
Series III: Art
Series IV: Printed Materials
Series V: Memorabilia
Series VI: Miscellaneous Printed Material
Series VII: Writings by and about Stephen and Cora Crane
Series VIII: Cataloged Correspondence re Stolper's bibliography of Craniana
Series IX: Stone, Wilbur Macy
Series X: Scrapbooks
Subjects
Crane, Cora, 1865 or 6-1910.; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924.; James, Henry, 1843-1916.; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Garland, Hamlin, 1860-1940.; Hubbard, Elbert, 1856-1915.; Haggard, H. Rider (Henry Rider), 1856-1925.; Sussex (England)--Social life and customs.; American literature--20th century.; Women authors.; Articles.; Autographs.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Photoprints.; Pictures.; Poems.; McNeil, Hammond P.,--Mrs.; Authors, American.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1952 M-52 Purchase
Alternate Formats
Boxes 1-9 (except for Crane cataloged documents), 12, and 20 are on microfilm.
- Series I: Cataloged Material
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    Boxes 1-9 (except for Crane cataloged documents), 12, and 20 are on microfilm
    - Original catalog of the collection. Description of the collection (Box 1)
    - Adams, Geoffrey Charlton
    - Adams, Samuel Hopkins
    - Adelme, Edith I.
    - Alexander, Eben
    - Allen, P. H. (for Simon Brentano)
    - Anderson, Mary, Countess de Navarro
    - Appleton, Daniel
    - Appleton, D & Co.
    - Avery, Van B.
    - Aylward, Eleanor S.
    - Babcock, Emma W.
    - Bacheller, Irving
    - Bacheller & Johnson Syndicate
    - Baldwin, Robert S.
    - Bancroft, Samuel Jr.
    - Bangs, John Kendrick
    - Barr, Mabel (Mrs. Mark Barr)
    - Barr, Mark
    - Barr, Robert
    - Barron, Oswald
    - Barrows, Samuel J.
    - Barry, John
    - Bass, Abba
    - Bass, John
    - Belasco, David
    - Beveridge, David
    - Bierce, Ambrose
    - Bigelow, Edith
    - Bigelow, Poultney
    - Bleyer, Julius
    - Block, Rudolph
    - Bok, Edward W
    - Bowen, Ethel
    - Bowen, F. A.
    - Bowen, Frederick L.
    - Bowen, Helen
    - Bowen, Millicent
    - Boyce, Neith
    - Boyd, Nathan E.
    - Brabazon, H. B.
    - Bray, Florence
    - Brooke, Emma
    - Brooke, Mary E.
    - Brookfield, A. M.
    - Brookfield, Olive
    - Bross, E. C.
    - Brown, Caroline L. (Mrs. Curtis Brown)
    - Brown, Curtis
    - Brown, Samuel
    - Brown, Shipley & Co.
    - Bullen, Mrs. A.
    - Burke, Lily
    - Caine, Sir Thomas Henry Hall (Box 2)
    - Campbell, W. W.
    - Carman, Bliss
    - Carter, J. R.
    - Chamberlin, J. E.
    - Chase, R. Allen
    - Choate, Joseph H.
    - Churchill, Lady Randolph
    - Clarke, William
    - Cochrane, Henry Clay
    - Cockran, Mr.
    - Colwell, J. C.
    - Colwell, Sarah Brant
    - Combe, Amy
    - Conrad, Jessie
    - Conrad, Joseph
    - Conrad, Mr. and Mrs. Joseph
    - Cowlishaw, W. H.
    - Crane, Aunt Abbie
    - Crane, Beatrice (Mrs. Jeffree)
    - Crane, Cora
    - Crane, E. B.
    - Crane, George P.
    - Crane, Helen
    - Crane, Mamie
    - Crane, Mary Frances (Mrs. Walter)
    - Crane, R. Newton
    - Crane, Stephen
    - Crane, Mr & Mrs. Walter
    - Crane, William
    - Cranshaw, Mary
    - Creelman, Alice B.
    - Croly, Jane Cunningham
    - Curtis, Cyrus H. K.
    - Cushing, Marshall
    - Dargan, Pegram (Box 3)
    - Davidson, John Russell
    - Davis, Richard Harding
    - Davis, Walter J.
    - Deats, H. E.
    - De Friese, Katherine
    - De Friese, Lafayette Hoyt
    - Dilke, Sir Charles Wentworth
    - Dudley, Winfield W.
    - Dunn, J. Nichol
    - Dunn, John
    - Dunne, F. P.
    - Dunston, Thomas W.
    - Edwards, E. J.
    - Edwards, William Croswell
    - Elliott, Captain G. F.
    - Everett, Captain H. J.
    - Fay, May Tifft (Mrs. Arthur Fay)
    - Fiedler, Ernst
    - Field, W. H.
    - Field-King, Julia
    - Fisher, W. J.
    - Flower, Clement
    - Floyd, Robert Mitchell
    - Follet, W. Morris
    - Forbes-Bentley, Florence
    - Forbes-Robinson, Sir J.
    - Ford, A. G.
    - Ford, Ford Madox See: Hueffer, Ford Madox
    - Forman, Kate Lyon "Frederic"
    - Fraenkel, Dr. Albert
    - Frankau, Frank Danby
    - Frankau, Julia (Mrs. F. D.)
    - Fraser, Mrs. Helen Mary
    - Fraser, John Foster
    - Frederic, Harold
    - Frewen, Clara
    - Frewen, Moreton
    - Frewer, Cyril C.
    - Frewer, Rev. G. Ernest
    - Frewer, L. C.
    - Friedman, Carl A.
    - Fritot, Alphonse W.
    - Fuller, Samuel Richard
    - Galloway, Tod B.
    - Garland, Hamlin
    - Garmeson, J.
    - Garnett, Edward
    - Garrison, Wendell P.
    - Gilder, Joseph B.
    - Gill, Margaret
    - Gillette, William
    - Gissing, George
    - Godkin, E. L.
    - Goetz, Phillip B.
    - Goode, W. A. M.
    - Goodman, Richard, Jr.
    - Grady, Thomas F.
    - Griffin, Mrs. C. L.
    - Guiney, Louise Imogene
    - Haggard, Sir Henry Rider (Box 4)
    - Haggard, Mrs. H. Ryder
    - Hale, Edward Everett, Jr.
    - Hale, Phillip L.
    - Halsey, Francis W.
    - Hamilton, James
    - Hanauer, A. M.
    - Hanson, P. (for George Wyndham)
    - Harriman, Karl Edwin
    - Harris, Frank
    - Harte, Walter Blackburn
    - Harvard Lampoon, Literary Editor
    - Hasbrook, C. E.
    - Hawkins, Willis B.
    - Hay, Helen
    - Hayes, Mr.
    - Hearst, William Randolph
    - Henkels, Stan V.
    - Harringshaw, Thomas W.
    - Hewett, G. C.
    - Hilliard, John N.
    - Hind, Lewis
    - Hitchcock, Ripley
    - Hofer, E.
    - Holder, Mary (Aunt)
    - Hollister, F. M.
    - Horner, R. J. & Co.
    - Howard, Walter
    - Howell, Ethel
    - Howells, William Dean
    - Huardel, P. G. & Co.
    - Hubbard, Elbert
    - Hubbell, Mark T.
    - Hueffer, Ford Madox
    - Humphrey, George P.
    - Hurst, Florence
    - Hurst, Hal
    - Huxton, H. R.
    - Incorp. Soc. for Psychical Research
    - Jackson, Frederick A.
    - James, Henry
    - Jewett, Sarah Orne
    - Johnson, R. U.
    - Jordan, Marcia B.
    - Jorissen, E.
    - Kanai Kodak Klub
    - Kett, Laura B. Temple
    - Kipling, Rudyard
    - Knapp, Adeline
    - Kropotkin, Princess Sophie
    - Leathers, J. W.
    - Leighton, Byron
    - Lewis, E. St. Elmo
    - Liefeld, E. Theo.
    - Little, Charles J.
    - Lord, Chester A.
    - Love, Edith Maclure
    - Lucas, Arthur
    - Lynch, George
    - Lynch, Mary
    - MacArthur, J.
    - McCarthy, Charlotte
    - McCarthy, Justin Huntly
    - McCawley, Major Charles L.
    - McClure, W.?
    - McClure, Robert
    - McGrath, Ellen M.
    - McIntosh, Burr William
    - Maclaglen, Dr. J. T.
    - McPhelim, E. J.
    - McQuilkin, Mr.
    - Mabie, Hamilton W.
    - Major, George MacDonald
    - Mallet, A.
    - Manchester, Consuelo, Duchess of
    - Marriot, M. Grace
    - Marriot-Watson, H. B.
    - Marshall, J. D.
    - Martin, Edward S.
    - Mason, A. E. W.
    - Mattis, L.
    - Methuen & Co.
    - Meyer, Otto A.
    - Michelson, Charles
    - Milner, A.
    - Moore, F. Frankfort
    - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Sr.
    - Morris, George P.
    - Morris, Lizzie
    - Myers, Prof. J. W.
    - Nicholson, Meredith
    - Noguchi, Yone
    - Northern Newspaper Syndicate
    - Norton, Charles E.
    - Osborne, W. W.
    - Palli, J. L. (Box 5)
    - Parke, Clara Cahill
    - Parker, Judge Alton B.
    - Parkin, Thomas
    - Parrish, Kate B.
    - Pawling, Sydney
    - Pease, Edward R.
    - Pease, Mrs. Marjory
    - Peck, J. K.
    - Peeke, Rachel G.
    - Perris, G. H.
    - Philson, Emma
    - Pinero, Arthur Wing
    - Pinero, Mrs. Arthur Wing
    - Pinker, James B.
    - Plant, Alfred T.
    - Plant, Henry T.
    - Porter, A. M.
    - Porter, Antoinette
    - Porter, Linn Boyd
    - Prang, L.
    - Prescott
    - Ptolemeon, Antoneon
    - Pugh, Edwing
    - Putnam, G. H.
    - Putnam, Herbert
    - Ralli, Mrs. Stephen
    - Reeve, James Knapp
    - Remington, Frederic
    - Reynolds, Paul R.
    - Rhodes, Harrison G.
    - Richards, Grant
    - Richie, Edith
    - Richie, Ford
    - Richie, Mary
    - Riding, William H.
    - Robins, Elizabeth
    - Roche & Son
    - Rogers, Sherman S.
    - Rooney, John
    - Roosevelt, Theodore
    - Ruddy, H. S.
    - Russell, Dick
    - Russell, Ernest E.
    - Schuyler, William (Box 6)
    - Scott-Stokes, Ethel
    - Scott-Stokes, John
    - Shaw, George Bernard
    - Shaw, George K.
    - Shepard, Fred J.
    - Sherman, Frank Dempster
    - Simpson, James W.
    - Skinner, Charles M.
    - Sladen, Douglas
    - Smalley, Frank
    - Smith, Mrs. E. B. Dugald
    - Smith, F. Hopkinson
    - Society of American Women in London
    - Somerset, H. Somers
    - Stedman, Srthur
    - Stewart, Major General Sir Norman, C. B.
    - Stokes, Frederick A., Co.
    - Stone, Herbert Stuart
    - Sutre, Alfred
    - Tallmadge & Tallmadge
    - Tauchnitz, Baron
    - Thomas, Brandon
    - Tilletson & Son
    - Trudeau, E. L.
    - Tuohy, James M.
    - Tyler, Moses Coit
    - Vernall
    - Von Kahlden
    - Waldemar, Adrien
    - Walker, Elliot
    - Walther, Dr. Otto
    - Warner, Charles Dudley
    - Warner, E. T.
    - Warner, George Coffing
    - Wells, Catherine
    - Wells, George Herbert
    - Westminster Gazette
    - Wharton, George F.
    - Whibley, Charles
    - Whigham, J. A.
    - White, P.
    - Williams, Kathleen
    - White, James J. & Co.
    - Williams, S. M.
    - Williams, Talcott
    - Windust, Ernest
    - Winship, A. E.
    - Woolley, Charles Woodruff
    - Wrench?, I.
    - Wright, Louis
    - Wyndham, George
    - Young, James C.
    - Young, Wickham W.
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscripts and Documents
    - Crane, Stephen. Prose, A-O (Box 7)
    - Crane, Stephen. Prose, P-Z (Box 8)
    - Poetry
    - Documents, n.d. & 30 April 1895 - 29 Dec.1899
    - Crane, Cora. Manuscripts and documents. (Box 9)
- Series II: Arranged Series
  - Subseries II.1: Documents
    - Brown, Shipley & Co. (Box 10)
    - Bowen, Frederick L.
    - McCalla, Bowman Henry
    - McNiel, Hammond P.
    - Plant, A. T.
    - Scott-Stokes, John
  - Subseries II.2: Manuscripts
    - Conrad, Joseph
    - Koran. 15 century.
      [one leaf in the Nask and Sulus style]
    - Linson, Corwin Knapp
    - Morse, Josephine
    - "Pike's Ms"
    - Walker, Elliot
- Series III: Art
  - Crane, Helen (cataloged)
  - Crane, Mary Helen Peck (Crane's mother) 1. Painting on a wooden board showing a landscape of hills, lake and a man in a boat which closely resembles the sketch opposite p. 332 in "Wyoming" by george Peck entitled "Bidlack at Schickshinny.", (12.5 x 14.5 in. )
    [In mapcase 14/13/8]
  - Crane, Mary Helen Peck 2. Pastel still life of a white pitcher and fruit, (11 x 14 in. )
  - Murray-Hamilton, Mary Helen Crane (Crane's oldest sister) 1. Painting of pineapples, unframed., (12 x 16 in. )
  - Crane Family. Photographs, (5 items. ) (Box 11)
  - Crane Family Photographs, ( 5 prints. )
  - Crane, Stephen Photographs, (11 items. )
  - Crane, Stephen and Cora Photograph, ( 1 item )
  - Miscellaneous photographs relating to Cora Crane., (5 items )
  - Henry James Photograph of Henry James (with doughnut).
  - James, Henry and Cora Crane Photograph of Henry James and Cora Crane.
  - Conrad, Borys and John Photograph of Joseph Conrad's children, Borys and John Conrad.
  - Photograph of Cora Crane's family and friends., (7 items )
  - Crane, Cora. Photograph negative of beach scene.
  - Photographs of Key West, Fla. 2 items
  - Frederic, Barry and Heloise Photograph (picture postcard) of Barry and Heloise Frederic.
  - Hollenbeck, Jennie Photograph of Jennie Hollenbeck
  - Glynes, Mrs. Dietz Photograph of Mrs. Dietz Glynes
  - Alexander, Eben Photograph of Eben Alexander
  - Photographs of Brede Place., (21 items )
  - Crane, Cora Photographs of Cora Crane., (9 items )
  - Budd, Ernest Photograph of Ernest Budd and friends.
  - C. Gouliclin Photograph of C. Gouliclin, Athens, [n.d.]
  - Thiers, Albert Gérard Photograph.
  - Photograph of New Jersey Conference Seminary
  - Photograph of Cora Crane postcards in the Jacksonville, Fla. Public Library.
  - Cora Crane Greco-Turkish war clippings (Box 12)
- Series IV: Printed Materials
  - Above all things
  - Active service
    [Laminated in a board portfolio shelved in oversize 14/13/8]
  - Adventures of a novelist
  - Ambrose Bierce and Stephen Crane
  - At Asbury park
  - Ballydehob
  - The chatter of a death-demon froma tree top
  - City urchin and the chaste villagers
  - Clippings about Crane., (15 items)
  - A desertion
  - Free silver down in Mexico
  - Galveston, Texas in 1895
  - George's mother
  - God rest ye merry gentlemen
  - Great battles
    [See: Pictures of a War]
  - His new mittins
  - I have heard the sunset song of the birches
  - In the tenderloin
  - Kipling on Wounds in the Rain
  - The little regiment
  - Maggie
  - The man from Duluth
  - Mardi Gras festival
  - Mexico. Newspaper article
  - New York's bicycle speedway
  - New York police episode. Clippings concerning this incident
  - The open boat
  - Pictures of a war
  - Poetry. Reviews and notices., ( 5 items )
  - Red badge of courage. Reviews., (9 items. )
  - Roof gardens and gardeners of New York
  - Roof gardens, New York
  - The second generation
  - Sign of the lantern club
  - Six years afloat
  - A souvenir and a medley
  - The squire's madness
  - This majestic lie
  - Two uncollected articles
  - You tell me this is God?
  - The veteran
  - War vignettes. A run to Cuba.
  - When men stumble
  - Whilomville stories
  - Whilomville stories. Reviews.
  - Works. General discussion of, in periodicals.
  - The wreck of the new era
  - Scarf, J. Thomas War correspondents of, 1860-1865
- Series V: Memorabilia
  - Crane, Cora: "Rose picked at 'Bride Place' (from one that I planted in 1899"); envelope; passenger list; Bazaar announcement., (1 folder ) (Box 13)
  - Buttons, handles., (9 items. 1 folder)
  - Cards of introduction., (1 folder)
  - Society of American Women in London, (4 items. 1 folder )
  - Howorth, George: The Restoration of Oil Painting. Boston, 1859.
  - Pamphlet by Cora Crane's father, autographed by Cora
  - Crane, Stephen: Advertisements for Wounds in the Rain., (3 items. 1 folder )
  - The Black Riders. Announcements and catalogues of Copeland and Day, publishers. Boston, 1895., (1 folder)
  - Burlesques of Stephen Crane., (1 folder)
  - The Ghost. program of the play., (3 copies. 1 folder)
  - Crane, Stephen and Cora Crane Clippings (miscellaneous)., (1 folder )
  - Crane, Stephen Clippings relating to Crane's death, posthumous works, etc., ( 1 folder )
  - Memorabilia: napkin holder; lottery tickets; rail ticket; ticket; Mexican National Athletic Club membership ticket; Modern Novel Club programs for 1898-1899; ad. for Wounds in the Rain; photo. of bust; D. Appleton and Co. ad.; United States Marine Corps letter re. Crane; restaurant menu.
  - Handkerchief in envelope., (1 folder)
  - "Commodore" wreck clippings., (1 folder)
  - Obituaries and biographical material
  - Newspaper biographies.
- Series VI: Miscellaneous Printed Material
  - City of Boston Document No. 120, 1873., (1 folder )
  - Society of the Philistines Souvenir menu of dinner in honor of Crane, ((3 copies) )
  - Society of the Philistines; Dinner invitation; reply to the Invitation by Crane; general invitation., ((3 copies) )
  - Proofs of the Stephen Crane catalog and correspondence relating to the catalog. (Box 14)
  - Stolper, Benjamin John Reeman Bibliographical notes on cards, (1 file box ) (Box 15)
  - Stolper, Benjamin John Reeman Clippings relating to Crane, (1 folder )
  - A brick from Stephen Crane's birthplace, 14 Mulberry Place, Newark, NJ (Box 16)
- Series VII: Writings by and about Stephen and Cora Crane
  - The War Dispatches of Stephen Crane; The Poems of Stephen Crane; Dark Rider; articles, reviews, etc. (Box 17)
  - Writings by and about Stephen Crane continued (Box 18)
  - Stolper, Benjamin John Reeman Stephen Crane correspondence: leads, (1 folder ) (Box 19)
- Series VIII: Cataloged Correspondence re Stolper's bibliography of Craniana
  - Abbott, Willis J.
  - Adler, Elmer
  - Alvord, Thos. G., Sr.
  - Anderson, Harold M.
  - Beamish, Richard J.
  - Blythe, Samuel G.
  - Bohnenberger, Carl
  - Brisbane, Arthur
  - Caddle, B. B.
  - Clark, Barrett H.
  - Crane, G. Archer
  - Crone, F. W.
  - Curran, Henry H.
  - Downey, Fairfax
  - Fish, Helen Dean
  - Gavin, John H.
  - Green, Francis Harvey
  - Harper & Brothers
  - Heflin, Wilson L.
  - Herzberg, Max
  - Hicks, Granville
  - Hoffman, Dr. M. David
  - Hughes, J. Winifred
  - Hughes, Rupert
  - Huyke, Juan B.
  - Klasen, J. H.
  - Knopf, Alfred A.
  - Koischwitz, Otto
  - Lielker, Minna J.
  - Linson, Corwin K.
  - Longstreet, E. S.
  - Lyman, R. H.
  - MacAlarney, Robert Emmet
  - McCardell, Roy L.
  - McCready, E. W.
  - March, Alden
  - Meriweather, W. S.
  - Michelson, Charles
  - North, J. M., Jr.
  - Phillips, John S.
  - Pew, Marlen E.
  - Peck, George L.
  - Pittenger, George W.
  - Rogge, E. P.
  - Russell, Charles Edward
  - Seibold, Louis
  - Seitz, Don C.
  - Shinn, Everett
  - Sloan, John
  - Smith, E. L.
  - Smith, Ernest G.
  - Stallman, R. W.
  - Starrett, Vincent
  - Stechert, G. E. & Co.
  - Steffens, Lincoln
  - Stolper, B. J. R.
  - Vila, Joe
  - Walton, Perry
  - Webb, J. H.
  - White, Jesse D.
  - Willis, W. A.
  - Winterich, John T.
  - Young, Nathan
- Series IX: Stone, Wilbur Macy
  A collection of letters to Stone relating to his reprint of a Stephen Crane publication in The Bookman:
  - Dreher, Monroe F.
  - Garrett, S.
  - Herzberg, Max J.
  - Mangione, Jerre G.
  - Molyneaux, Peter
  - Van Dyne, Catherine
- Series X: Scrapbooks
  - "Literary Scraps", (1 volume ) (Box 20)
    [Clippings re. Crane.]
  - "The University Herald" Vol XVIII, No., 1, Sept. 1889 - Vol. XIX, No. 9, June 1891.
  - "The University Herald" Vol. XXI, No. 1, Oct. 1892 - Vol XXIII, No. 10, July 1895.
  - Scrapbook of printed stories by Crane (Box 21)
    [Lacking rear cover, damaged by water]
  - Scrapbook of stories and articles by Crane
    [Both boards and spine detached, in fragile condition]
  - Photograph albums, (2 volumes )
    [In fragile condition]